Good morning everybody. Okay, today's דף Daf *daf* is כ"ג *Chaf Gimmel*
and we pick up on the משנה Mishna, *Mishna* of כ"ב עמוד
ב' *Chaf Beis Amud Beis*. Oh no, I'm sorry, I correct that,
today's דף daf. *daf* is... I was testing you, I was testing
you. Okay, today's דף *daf* is כ"ד *Chaf Daled*. Today's דף *daf*
is כ"ד *Chaf Daled* and we pick up at the new פרק
*perek* at the bottom of כ"ג עמוד ב' *Chaf Gimmel Amud Beis*.
Okay, here we go. ארוסה ושומרת יבם Arusa v'Shomeres Yavam, *Arusa v'shomeret
yavam*, now that we've sort of gone through the procedure, okay, and
by the way, I want to remind everybody, contrary to the popular
myth or imagination,
not only in the תורה Torah *Torah* does she not die, but
even in the משנה Mishna *Mishna* and in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
it never says she dies. The one line is get her out
lest she make the עזרה טמא *Azarah tamei* and the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* interpreted that to mean lest she become a נדה *niddah*. So
just want to remind you about that because that's not the popular
imagination. Anyway, turning to the next פרק *perek*, now that we're done
with the whole process, we began...
I don't know where that comes from.
I don't know. Now that we're done with the whole process, we
go back and we look again at sort of a classic halachic
analysis. Right, normally it's unusual, right, not unheard of, like you get
it a lot in קדשים *Kodashim* or whatever, but unusual for a
series of משניות *mishnayot* to be describing a step-by-step process. Right, normally
it's sort of talking about the criteria, the categories, who's in, who's
out, etc. So that's the type of thing that now we shift
back to, identifying which types of people qualify and don't qualify and
similar issues.
So, ארוסה Arusa ושומרת יבם Yavam לא שותות ולא נוטלות Lo Shotot
Velo Notlot. כתובתה *Arusa v'shomeret yavam lo shotot v'lo notlot ktubatah*. So
a woman who is an ארוסה Arusa, *arusa*, she's betrothed, she accepted
קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin* like the nowadays the ring or whatever from the
man, which means that legally she's married. If she commits adultery it
is a same act of adultery and she would be executed if
there were witnesses. It means that she would be forbidden to her
husband, the children would be ממזרים mamzerim, *mamzerim*, the whole nine yards.
The only difference is is that the marriage is at this stage
on paper. It has not yet begun a lived married life together,
which means that the sort of reciprocal obligations aren't present. They're not
having sex, they're not making house together, etc. That's the ארוסה Arusa.
*arusa*. The שומרת יבם Shomeres Yavam *shomeret yavam* is the woman whose
husband died leaving her with no children and now there's a brother
and she is awaiting that brother to either do יבום Yibum, *yibbum*,
she is awaiting יבום Yibum, *yibbum* or possibly חליצה Chalitzah *chalitzah*. In
that case, there's only an איסור לאו Issur Lav *issur lav* for
her to let's say sleep with another man or marry another man.
Nevertheless, though, what's present now is seen as זיקה *zika*, some type
of continuation of the relationship with of the marriage with the dead
brother and that's sort of existing quasi
in potential, quasi in potential with the current brother. So the יבם
*yavam* is
kinui on her? Yeah. Is there more than one? Like... Well
the הלכה Halacha *halacha*
is לא
שותות ולא נוטלות
Lo
Shotot
Velo Notlot כתובתה *lo shotot v'lo notlot ktubatah*. So if the husband
or the brother does קינוי Kinui? *kinui* and then the woman goes
into seclusion then they cannot be forced to drink and because they
cannot be forced to drink and but they do become forbidden as
a סוטה Sotah? *sotah*, that's implicit. So here's a woman that's going
to be forbidden to her husband because she's a סוטה Sotah *sotah*,
not definitely committed adultery but suspected and it's gone through the process.
So she's forbidden to her husband and she can't drink to resolve
it, so she doesn't get the כתובתה *ktubata*. And we're going to
discuss in a minute what happens when it's nobody's fault, but the
basic rule is when it's her fault that she can't drink she
doesn't get the כתובה Ketubah *ktuba*, when it's his fault or when
it's her fault the whole situation she doesn't get the כתובה Ketubah.
*ktuba*, when it's his fault she does get the כתובה Ketubah. *ktuba*.
This is considered to be her fault because even though it's nobody's
fault that she can't go through the procedure, she's just an ארוסה
Arusa *arusa* not a נשואה nesua *nesua*, nevertheless, it's seen as she
didn't have to go in private in seclusion with this man after
the husband warned her. So therefore it's a case that can't be
resolved, she's forbidden, she's seen as the sort of responsible party and
therefore she does not get a כתובה kesuvah. *ktuba*. Now, the issue
about the יבם *yavam* is interesting because רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, you
know, we discussed earlier what happens if a שומרת יבם Shomeres Yavam
*shomeret yavam* sleeps actually knows is known to have slept with another
man. Is she forbidden to her husband or not? Right, and part
of that gets to the question or her husband, the brother, is
the brother now not able to do יבום Yibum, *yibbum*? Is that
how much do we sort of see that like a woman who
committed adultery not because of the gravity of the sin but because
there's a quasi marriage that has continued how much would that make
her forbidden legally on the brother? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says even
if she weren't forbidden on the brother, the brother would be entitled
to say but I I refuse to marry such a woman. So
that's why she would be divorced without getting her כתובה kesuvah. *ktuba*.
תוספות Tosfot *Tosafot* disagrees. תוספות Tosfot *Tosafot* says we learned earlier that
if a woman would not be forbidden had she done the act,
then she cannot become a סוטה Sotah, *sotah*. She cannot become forbidden
and being suspected of having done the act. That sort of makes
sense, right? How how does her status of a סוטה Sota, *sotah*
make her more forbidden than if it was known that she had
done it? So תוספות *Tosafot*... says we're working with the position that
she is forbidden on her husband or he gives a variant reading
which is a little complicated I'm not going to get into but
anyway the simple explanation is we're working with the assumption that if
this שומרת יבמה slept with another man she would be forbidden to
her husband or not her husband the brother. Yes.
Is there anything to say about the
language לא נוטלות כתובתן Lo Notlot Ketubatam instead of ותצא בלא כתובה?
Ve'teitzei Blo Ketuvah?
Oh
I don't know that's an interesting question. Why doesn't it say תצא?
Teitzei? Why doesn't it say תצא? Teitzei? Yeah it's a good point
because תצא Teitzei really is more relevant but the basic point is
we're going to see cases that it's going to be that they
are נוטלות כתובתן. Notlot Ketubatam. So the easy thing to do is
לא שותות ולא נוטלות. Lo Shotot Velo Notlot First of all there's
a parallel לא שותות Shotot ולא נוטלות and then we're going to
have cases of לא שותות ונוטלות. Lo Shotot Ve'notlot. So it's just
the easier sort of parallel yeah.
If there's more than one brother is anyone entitled to do the
קינוי? Kinui?
Oh that is a good question. If there's more than one brother
is anyone entitled to do the קינוי? Kinui Yeah that's a really
good question and if he did I don't think we discussed it
either and if she becomes forbidden on one brother who did the
קינוי Kinui does she remain permissible to the other brothers like it's
a really good question. Okay שנאמר Shene'emar
אשר תשטה אשה תחת אישה Asher Tistei Ishah Tachat Ishah that a
woman will stray from her husband and אישה Ishah her husband means
like not her ארוס Arus but her אישה Ishah like a full
husband פרט לארוסה ושומרת יבמה Prat Le'arusah Veshomeret Yavama to exclude the
cases where the marriage is not yet full. Now of course then
the question would be so how do you know that they can
make her into a סוטה? Sota, How do you know that you
can do the קינוי kinuy, and that that part of the פרשה
Parshah still applies? And the גמרא Gemara will learn that out that
that part of the פרשה Parshah still applies even though you can't
finish the procedure. Okay אלמנה לכהן גדול Almanah Lekohein Gadol גרושה וחלוצה
לכהן הדיוט Grushah Vachalutzah Lekohein Hedyot let's say the marriage even before
she was suspected of committing adultery let's say the marriage was already
forbidden from a certain perspective. Now if it's forbidden like an איסור
כרת Issur Kareit like it's a what do you call it like
it's one of the cases of incest
then the marriage isn't binding but a marriage that's forbidden by an
איסור לאו Lav the best examples are איסורי כהונה Issurei Kehunah like
גרושה Grushah and חלוצה Chalutzah etc. could also be the case of
a ממזר Mamzer נתין Netin עמוני Amoni מואבי Moavi etc. but you
know things that are simple negative prohibition the marriage actually is binding
even though it's in violation. So the question is if somebody's in
a marriage that's a binding marriage that's in violation of the law
because it's transgressing one of these negative prohibitions is the husband entitled
to charge his wife and to make her into a סוטה Sota.
and to bring her to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash if at
some level we should be saying you guys shouldn't be remaining married
anyway you should be getting divorced regardless. Okay so that's what it
talks about. So let's take a look. If a כהן גדול Kohein
Gadol is married to a widow or a גרושה Grushah a divorcee
or חלוצה Chalutzah a woman who's undergone חליצה is married to a
כהן הדיוט Kohein Hedyot there's a question of חלוצה דאורייתא Chalutzah De'oraisa
or דרבנן De'rabanan the בבלי Bavli tends to assume it's דרבנן De'rabanan
for her to marry a כהן Kohein ממזרת ונתינה לישראל Mamzeret Unetina
Leyisrael or a woman who is a ממזר Mamzer or נתין Netin
who is one of the Canaanite tribes or whatever I don't want
to get into נתין Netin that's a whole discussion. Anyway married to
a normal ישראל Yisrael
or בת ישראל לממזר ונתין Bat Yisrael Lemamzer Unetin let's say it's
not the woman's issue it's the man's issue she's a totally normally
born Jewish woman and he is a ממזר Mamzer or נתין. Netin.
In all those cases though there's a negative prohibition that sort of
relates about the marriage or מחזיר גרושתו.
Machazir Grushaso.
Yeah I guess that could be.
Good point. לא שותות ולא נוטלות כתובתן. Lo Shotot Velo Notlot Ketubatam.
In those cases she doesn't drink because it is not considered אישה
Ishah in the sense of a marriage that should be remaining. It
is binding but it's not a marriage that's a legitimate marriage that
should be remaining. So
but also she doesn't get the כתובה kesuvah. because again you know
she is in no way nobody is to blame that it's not
that she's not שותות Shotot. but she is still the one who
went into seclusion after she was warned so that is seen that
if you can't finish the process she doesn't get a כתובה. kesuvah.
ואלו לא שותות ולא נוטלות כתובה. Ve'eilu Lo Shotot Velo Notlot Ketuvah.
That's interesting we just gave a list of people that were לא
שותות Shotot ולא נוטלות but that's based on people whose sort of
nature of their marriage is such that it excludes them from being
שותות. Shotot Now we're going to do with people who are not
שותות because of the way the process took place. So let's take
a look. האומרת טמאה אני Ha'omeret Temeah Ani if a woman confesses
her guilt ושבאו לה עדים שהיא טמאה Vesheba'u Lah Eidim Shehi Temeah
or if witnesses came that she had committed adultery so there's no
point in finishing the process
then והאומרת איני שותה Veha'omeret Eini Shota a woman who refuses to
drink. Okay now now what? No she's not לא לא כתובתה Lo
Lo Ketubatah the whole question was about
the שותות right?
Well right yeah after assuming that this is before the water right
there is some discussion after the name has been erased but we're
not getting into that now. So these cases she you know she's
refusing or she's confessing or we know so you're not going to
go through the process she's seen as the obstacle here you know
or she actually has committed it or confessed. committed it. So therefore
she does not get her כתובה kesuvah. *Kesuva*.
These are not ארוסות *Arussos*?
No, no, no, that's what I said. First category was about the
nature of the marriage. Now we're talking about normal marriage, the nature
of the process. Okay, now,
okay, איני משקה ושהבעל בא עליה *eini mashkeh v'shehaba'al ba aleha*. Now,
now though, we switch gears. אמר בעלה
*Amar Ba'alah*, let's say it's the husband who says איני משקה *eini
mashkeh*, you know what? I know I suspected her here but I
changed my mind. I refuse to go through with the process. ושהבעל
בא עליה *v'shehaba'al ba aleha*, or the husband is the one that
had sex with her after she doesn't literally have to mean by
there but after she became a סוטה Sota. *Sotah* before they did
this process and he's not allowed to. So in those cases, he's
the problem. Not only is he not allowed to but we say
if he did, then the waters won't work. So he clearly is
the one that's sort of preventing things from going forward. In that
case, נוטלות כתובה Kesuvah, ולא שותות *notlos kesuva v'lo shosos*. They do
get their כתובה Kesuvah. *kesuva*. They obviously can't drink but they do
get the כתובה Kesuvah. *kesuva*. He was to blame.
And they continue remaining married?
Right, because she's still a סוטה Sota. *Sotah*. Now, מתו בעליהן עד
שלא שתו *mesu ba'aleihen ad shelo shasu*. Let's say it's nobody's fault.
Let's say the husband dies. Okay? Act of God before they got
to it. Okay, so what do you do there? בית שמאי אומרים
נוטלות כתובה Kesuvah. ולא שותות *Beis Shammai omrim notlos kesuva v'lo shasos*,
that she gets the כתובה Kesuvah? *kesuva* and she doesn't drink. ובית
הלל אומרים או שותות או לא נוטלות כתובתן *u-Veis Hillel omrim o
shosos o lo notlos kesuvasan*. Either drink or don't get the כתובה
Kesuvah *kesuva*. And since you can't drink, don't get your כתובה Kesuvah.
*kesuva*. Okay, so this is a case where nobody is to blame.
Now, and but still בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* is willing to say
maybe since he's in the end the one who died, okay, so
even though he might not be to blame in a sense of
fault, he's the cause so whatever that's a simple sense, we'll see
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands it,
we sort of attribute the problem to him and therefore she's entitled
to get her כתובה Kesubah. *kesuva*. Okay, so that is the debate
there. So basically cases where either because of the nature of the
marriage or because of the nature of the proceedings you cannot drink
so and when it's the husband's fault, she does get her כתובה
Kesubah, *kesuva*. When it's not the husband's fault, she does not get
her כתובה *kesuva*. Now תוספות *Tosafos* raises the question which is
no, I thought this was תוספות *Tosafos*, hold on.
One minute.
No,
okay, I thought there was another point. Alright, let's go on. So
it says like this. Alright, where was I?
Alright, fine. So now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* continues. ועוברת חברתה ומינקת
חברתה *u’uveres chavairta u'meinekes chavairta*, לא שותות ולא נוטלות כתובה *lo shosos
v'lo notlos kesuva*. Now how about a woman who's not allowed, a
marriage that's not allowed, but it's not allowed because you're violating a
law, it's not allowed because you're violating some rabbinic issue, and even
the rabbinic issue it's not like חליצה *chalitzah* which is sort of
an expansion of a דאורייתא *de-Oraisa* and so on, it's
more emerged from a concern. What is that? That's a case of
מינקת חברתה *meinekes chavairta*
and עוברת חברתה *u'uveres chavairta*. And the problem here is so if
a man marries a woman while she is nursing a child, like
her husband died and now she's nursing a child that she was
left with from her previous husband, right? The concern is is that
if now this man will, he won't be concerned, it's not his
kid, and therefore he'll have sex with the woman and she'll get
pregnant and have another kid and that will sort of, there's a
concern that that will sort of compromise her care for or her
nursing of, you know, the current child. So in those types of
cases, so עוברת חברתה *u'uveres chavairta* is let me just tell you
one minute.
Married and was pregnant.
Right. Basically it's the same point. We don't want her to, if
she now needs to be spending like the assumption is like the
next two years raising and spending a lot of focused care on
this current child. So if it's your child, you the man, right,
and you decide to have kids in quick succession, then that's your
choice. But here we're concerned that he's not going to make a
choice for
the welfare of the child because it's not his child and they'll
have a kid within two years' time and that won't be necessarily
the best decision for the current unborn or newborn child. So therefore
we say that he should not marry her
until during that period for two years. Actually it's interesting
because it raises an interesting question that הרב יהודה Yehuda הרצל הנקין
*Rav Yehuda Herzl Henkin* basically said, you know, that he would regularly,
not הרב יהודה הרצל הנקין *Rav Yehuda Herzl Henkin*, הרב יוסף אליהו
הנקין *Rav Yosef Eliyahu Henkin* said that in Lithuania whatever, just in
general, he would regularly give היתרים *heterim* for women to use birth
control for two years after they had had a child so that
they could focus on the current child. And actually he would extend
it, he said three or four years or whatever, but here you
already see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in a sense, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* isn't saying you can or you may or you should
use birth control but it's talking about like an acknowledgment as to
having children in quick succession could be not for the welfare and
if it's not your child we're concerned you won't make the right
decision. So anyway so...
Right, and you say on the books it's a law not to
marry a
woman within two years of having a kid? Yeah. Yes. That's הלכה?
halacha, Yeah.
Wow. Okay. So he went then and he did this, which is
a rabbinic issue, it's not like an issue about personal status or
whatever, it's rabbinic concern around these
cases. So what's the הלכה halacha now? And then קינה ונסתרה. Kinah
V'Nistarah. So is this considered like the case where they're where they've
where they are vi- where the marriage is in violation of a
biblical prohibition, that he's not entitled to to make her drink because
in some reason they shouldn't be married right now. So let's take
a look.
לא שותה ולא נוטלת כתובה דברי רבי מאיר. Lo Shotah V'Lo Notlet
Ketubah Divrei Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Meir applies the same principle. Yeah, for
whatever reason they shouldn't be married right now, you are not allowed
to go through with the procedure. She can't make her into a
סוטה, Sota: can't go through with the procedure. חכמים אומרים יכול הוא
להפרישה ולהחזירה לאחר זמן. Chachamim Omrim Yachol Hu L'Hafrishah U'Lehazir L'Achar Zman.
No, because in that type of a case he can, he wouldn't
have to divorce her. So if somebody went ahead and violated, they
could go ahead and live separate and they wouldn't have to get
divorced. We wouldn't demand that they got divorced. We would say, go
ahead, live separate and then start living together after the two years
are up, after the two years after child is two years old.
So since we wouldn't demand a divorce in that case, the marriage
is legitimate and therefore they can go ahead and and go and
do the and do the whole procedure, do the סוטות. Shotot. Okay.
איילונית
וזקנה ושאינה ראויה לילד. Aylonit Ve'Zkeinah U'She'eina Re'uya L'yeled. Now let's say
this woman is for one reason or another not able to have
children, okay? איילונית Aylonit is a woman that has very like masculine
characteristics and is considered not only to be infertile, but to actually
whatever, some I don't know what exact condition it's referring to, but
very sort of masculine characteristics. An old woman who can't have children,
שאינה ראויה לילד She'eina Re'uya L'yeled is interesting what it refers to.
רש"י Rashi says it meant that she drank some type of a
thing that made her that some sterilizing potion. תוספות has another explanation.
תוספות says why don't you just say עקרה, Akarah, which is like
the classic biblical example of a woman who can't have kids, an
infertile woman. But anyway, one way or another, it's a woman who
can't have kids. So in those cases should we say and the
man is married to her, now you could say, oh, so you
can't say ונקתה ונזרעה זרע, V'Nikta V'Nizra Zarah, you can't say the
opposite, maybe that's why they want to go through the process so
it's ונקתה ונזרעה זרע V'Nikta V'Nizra Zarah or something. But no, that's
not the issue. The issue is similar to what we've been discussing,
maybe we should say they shouldn't still be married. He should be
because the man has a מצוה Mitzvah of פרו ורבו, Pru U'Revu,
they need to get divorced, he needs to have kids, etc. So
is that enough of a reason to say since they shouldn't be
married, we won't sort of call it תחת אישה Tachat Isha like
the case of the לאו and the other cases and therefore she
can't make her drink?
Even if they've been married for 50 years, right? He can always
take another wife if his מצוה... Mitzvah...
let's see, that's going to be the response. Let's take a look.
What about a קטנה? Ketanah? Is this the same thing, because she's
fallen under this?
No, because she can eventually, it doesn't matter, though that eventually she
will. This is a case where clearly this marriage will not be
a marriage that will produce children. So therefore, what's the story? Okay.
Even if he already has enough children.
Ah, so that's the interesting question. But let's say he's already had
kids with another wife,
or what? Right. I think that's why it gave the example of
oh, you're right, because זקנה Zkeinah is just older. Right, they've been
married for 50 years. Yeah, right, right, right. So yeah, the presumption
is is that they haven't had kids, okay? together or even he
hasn't had and hasn't fulfilled פרו ורבו. Pru U'Revu. It's a very
strange idea because, you know, there's nothing intrinsically wrong with the marriage,
especially in a polygamous society you could marry another woman, right? But
anyway, and especially if you see it as his obligation, not their
obligation. So anyway, let's take a look. It says where are we?
לא נוטלת כתובה ולא שותה. Lo Notlet Ketubah Ve'Lo Shotah.
So the first ruling gave, yeah, sorry, they shouldn't be married, so
you don't get to do the drinking. רבי אליעזר אומר יכול הוא
וישא אשה אחרת ויפרוש ויעמוד עם זו. Rabbi Eliezer Omer Yachol Hu
Ve'Yissa Isha Acheret V'Yifros V'Ya'amod Im Zu.
What do you mean? He could always just marry another woman, he
can even keep this wife. Okay. So we'll see what that debate
is. I think our intuition goes with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer for
a variety of
reasons. Okay. Um so
she maybe should drink. Yeah. ושאר כל הנשים, Ve'Sha'ar Kol Ha'Nashim, all
other women, או שותות או לא נוטלות כתובה. O Shotot O Lo
Notlot Ketubah.
Okay, they get the choice. You're able to drink, so you either
drink, and if for whatever reason you're not going to drink, you
won't get your כתובה. אשת כהן שותה ומותרת לבעלה. Eshet Kohen Shotah
U'Mutereset L'Ba'alah.
The wife of a כהן, Kohen, once she drinks and she comes
out okay, she can go back to her husband. גמרא Gemara says
like פשיטא, Peshita, but given that the wife of a כהן Kohen
we know
is it's more easy for a woman to be forbidden to a
כהן, Kohen, we might have had some
הוה אמינא Hava Amina that
even after... sex. Or if he's doing, well, yeah, but okay, we'll
see. שותה, shosa, she will drink. Now, so that's interesting. Even though
he right now cannot have sex with her, that does not seem
somehow... that does not prevent her from, you know, from him saying
you shouldn't be sleeping with other men. Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara is
going to raise the issue that we're going to see in a
minute that a woman is only to go through this proceedings if
she has had... if her marriage has been consummated with her husband,
if they've had sex.
Okay, so this case of סריס Saris according to that understanding, which
isn't in the משנה, Mishnah but that's an understanding that the גמרא
Gemara adopts, would have to be a case that he became a
סריס Saris after their marriage had been consummated. All right, now, על
ידי כל העריות מקנאין חוץ מן הקטן וממי שאינו איש. Al yedai
kol arayot mikanyin chutz min hakatan u'mi she'aino ish. Let's say the
man suspects her not just of committing adultery, but of committing another
sexual sin, sleeping with her brother, I don't know. So, that's... that
the fact that there's another sin independent of adultery going on does
not prevent the proceedings of סוטה, Sotah because maybe you would have
sort of said like a קים ליה בדרבה מיניה. kim lei b'drabba
minei. One minute, or before we look at it as adultery, you
know, we have to sort of look at it through this other
lens. So, you can... the process still works even in those cases.
The exception, the one case that a person that he's suspected of
that would not make her a סוטה, Sotah, suspected of sleeping with
would either be a minor or somebody who is not a man.
So, we'll have to see, very suggestive phrase. I'll let you imagine
what that might be. We'll see it in the גמרא Gemara not
today.
Okay.
Yes,
a woman sleeping with a young boy is considered an עריות arayot
but not vice versa?
No, no, no, עריות, arayot, no, if these are not necessarily עריות...
arayot... if you're suspected of... a woman suspected of עריות, arayot, then
that is סוטה. Sotah Here is the only type of person a
woman could be suspected of sleeping with that would not make her
a סוטה. Sotah A min-... so this is not a sub-category... right,
this is not a sub-category of עריות, arayot, okay? This is what
type of men
can she be suspected of and still be a סוטה. Sotah, Yes,
עריות, arayot, but here are the following people that she could be
suspected of sleeping with that would not make her a סוטה: Sotah
a minor and somebody who's not an איש. ish.
But she is suspected of sleeping with him?
Or having sex, I'm being euphemistic.
No, thank you.
But
I was just wondering like with the- with the young kids, I
mean at some point there is a question of whether or not
he can have sex.
So, right, the assumption is that they can't have...
no, no, no, it's not that they physically couldn't, it's not that
they physically couldn't, it's that it's legally would not be significant. Okay,
what happens? All right, we'll see. Okay, but anyway, but now the
interesting question is, I would ask before you would get to מי
שאינו איש, mi she'aino ish, which is very, you know, subjective or
whatever, provocative, I would ask how about a non-Jew, right?
Let's say she's suspected of sleeping with a non-Jew, that's not mentioned
either, right? So, anyway, let's think about that.
Could be מי שאינו איש. mi she'aino ish.
I don't think that that would be
אינו איש. eino ish. Non-Jew would not be- okay, קטן katan also
is not תופס. tofes.
Right, I know, but things like- but at some point could be,
right? What is the common denominator?
I don't know, we'll see. Okay. ואלו שבית דין מקנאין להן. V'elu
she'beis din mikanyin lahen. Now the following women, their husband is not
in a position to do קינוי, kinuy. but the בית דין beis
din will step in on the husband's behalf if they sort of
see that the woman is acting in a way that are raising
suspicions and inappropriate and so on, which is interesting because it gets
to the question raised at the beginning of the מסכת masechet whether
אסור לקנאות assur l'kanos or מותר לקנאות. mutar l'kanos. So maybe this
is sort of saying like if בית דין beis din is stepping
in for an absent man, it sort of seems like it's sort
of saying מצוה mitzvah or חיוב לקנאות, chiyuv l'kanos, because who needs
בית דין beis din to get involved, right? Unless the point is
that you know that for a normal husband who is acting out
of his own jealousy and suspicions or whatever, that we might say
אסור לקנאות, assur l'kanos, you know, because you could have a lot
of other things going on there that's making you suspect your wife
than some objective concern. But maybe if it's a third party, right,
maybe our general principle could be אסור לקנאות assur l'kanos for the
husband, but if it's a third party that doesn't have a vested
interest, doesn't have passions about this whole thing or whatever and sees
a problem, maybe it is their responsibility if the husband isn't around
to do something to address it. So that's what our משנה Mishnah
says.
The following people,
well let's take a look. The following people the בית דין beis
din would step in and represent the husband and do קינוי. kinuy
By the way, that's a big חידוש. chiddush. Whoever said that anybody
could be empowered to do קינוי kinui. other than the husband? Okay,
anyway, the following people, the following cases: מי שנתחרש בעלה, Mi shenit-charesh
ba'alah, if the husband became a חרש, charesh, a deaf-mute, so he's
not considered to be a בר דעת, bar da'as, right? He's not
considered to have legal power anymore to
be... ואלו מי שנתחרש בעלה, v'elu mi shenit-charesh ba'alah, oh נשת-. nishta-.
ability שוטה shoteh is more like mental state, he's got, you know,
some very, some, he's, no, שוטה shoteh isn't demented, שוטה shoteh is
more like, like mental illness, thank you, או שהיה חבוש בבית האסורים,
o shehayah chavush beveit ha'asurim, or simply he's just not around, he's
being held in prison, and he's not able to see what his
wife is or isn't doing.
Would he take like, you know, he's like abroad, would that be
the same thing?
Maybe, although one may, maybe then a message should be sent and
he should come back and we shouldn't get involved at that stage.
He's gone out of his choice to be abroad.
Exactly, exactly. Here, exactly here, he's in, he cannot control the situation.
So in those cases בית דין Beis Din steps in. That's a
good point. לא להשקותה אמרו, lo lehashkotah amru, not that בית דין
Beis Din would ever be able to represent the husband to the
point of making her drink, אלא לפוסלה מכתובתה, ela lefoslah miktuvatah, which
is like, okay, well that's really helpful because then what they do
is they make her forbidden to her husband, and since it can't
be resolved, right, because the husband isn't in a position to bring
her to בית דין Beis Din and to the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, and בית דין Beis Din can't, the immediate result of them
stepping in is divorce and don't get your כתובה. So here's a
woman that בית דין Beis Din sees acting in a suspicious manner,
בית דין Beis Din could just say maybe force the husband to,
I don't know, to divorce her. Well, first of all, the question,
how do you get a divorce if the husband is a חרש
cheresh or שוטה? shoteh? So that's anyway a problem, but you know,
so the whole thing, only once if the husband gets better or
gets released, well maybe you could arrange for a גט get from
prison. Okay, but basically rather than somehow sort of saying like, anyway
what בית דין Beis Din is doing is that בית דין Beis
Din is not resolving, I mean the way they resolve the situation
is saying we're going to try to get a divorce here and
she won't get a
כתובה. רבי יוסי אומר אף להשקותה, Rabbi Yosi omer af lehashkotah, לכשיצא
בעלה מבית האסורים
ישקנה. liksheyeitzei ba'alah mibeit ha'asurim yashkenah. No, בית דין Beis Din actually
is empowered in order to make her drink,
לכשיצא בעלה מבית האסורים ישקנה, liksheyeitzei ba'alah mibeit ha'asurim yashkenah, because when
the husband does get freed he can make her drink on the
force of the בית דין's Beis Din קינוי. Kinoi, So actually this
is something that does not necessarily directly translate into divorce with no
כתובה. They are setting the ground, when the husband is at a
stage that he could divorce her, if he gets better from his
mental state or if he gets freed or whatever, maybe he doesn't
have to divorce her, he can go through with the process at
that stage.
In the meantime, she's like an עגונה. agunah.
She's an עגונה agunah anyway because she's not having sex with her
husband, right? I mean it's not getting sort of resolved as it
is anyway.
I mean for the divorce you were saying that she gets the
divorce?
Well she can't get a divorce when he's a חרש cheresh or
שוטה. shoteh. The only case she could get a divorce where the
husband is still not able to make her drink is from the
prison. He could arrange a גט get from the prison, right?
So if someone's not mentally able to, so you can't just like
have them hand over...
Yeah, so that becomes a real big case about can you do,
sort of like this is talking about the בית דין Beis Din
doing קינוי וסתירה kinui u'stirah on behalf of the husband. Can a
בית דין Beis Din give a גט get on behalf of the
husband when the husband is not, is mentally incapacitated, or is in
a coma, or whatever. There have been some recent cases in Israel
about that. Yeah, that's a real problem. Yeah.
Just a clarification on the, so the bottom line on the עריות
arayos is, right, capital crime, it's execution if all the conditions apply,
correct? The only difference is the theological dimension is כרת kares in
this case of עריות, arayos, in other words?
I mean, well, yes, some of the עריות arayos are only כרת.
kares. Adultery, adultery
is punishable by the death penalty. עריות, arayos, some are כרת, kares,
some are חייב מיתה. chayav misah. Right, but the bottom line... Yeah.
But the עריות arayos have nothing to do with the fact that
she's married. They're a completely different type of אזהרה. azarah. Right. So
maybe we would, so the חידוש chiddush is that we still frame
it in, we're able to still keep the marriage framing and go
through the סוטה Sotah process about that.
And if she goes through the סוטה, Sotah. it's not that she
survives, presumably means she's not guilty
of the עריות arayos either. Right, exactly.
It clears up both problems. Exactly.
So the first piece you're basically saying is that they're forcing a
divorce and not...
Well the funny thing is they're not, the only, the question is
right now nothing is happening because the husband's not in a state
to give a divorce. So in the first case, I mean, okay,
let's bracket for a moment giving a, arranging a divorce from prison.
Okay, right now nothing is happening. So in the first opinion, what
they're doing is they're laying the groundwork so that when, if and
when the husband is in a state to go ahead and come
back and be in and etc., etc., that now they've created a
situation where he's going to divorce his wife without כתובה. So as
opposed to had they done nothing,
then maybe then he would come back and maybe, I don't know,
continue living with her, or who knows what. So it's like interesting
about how, and is this really stopping her behavior? I mean look,
that's the other way of asking, like whose interests are they protecting?
Are they trying to stop her behavior? I mean if I was
in that situation, the woman, and I was saying like okay look,
either way right now I'm going to get divorced without כתובה. There's
no other way this can get resolved. Might as well just keep
up the affair, what do I got to lose at this stage,
right? So it's not really like stopping her behavior. So it seems
like it's like protecting his interests, right? So you're going to... You're
gonna come back, you're gonna find out about this, you're gonna want
to divorce your wife, but then you're gonna have to pay the
כתובה, so we're gonna get involved at this stage in order to,
say, you know, to protect your interests and make it easier, and
maybe you won't want to divorce your wife and we think you
should divorce your wife, so we're gonna like grease the, you know,
the what's it called, grease the wheels or something, Napab, wheels or
whatever, you know, skid, so that
to make it that much easier. It's interesting, right? It's like I
think what's understood trying to represent his interests, but the problem is
how it doesn't exactly play out that way, you know.
We know he's, right?
If she's been if she cheated on him, he doesn't pay the
כתובה.
That's correct, but we don't know. All we know is that they
made her into a סוטה Sotah. through going through the process. We
don't know what she actually did.
But he's never going to get better.
Right.
You mean because he wouldn't be able to actually prove.
Right, exactly. There's no proof. There's just suspicion.
She went into seclusion, they'll do קינוי, Kinoi she goes into seclusion,
we're never we don't have any evidence that she actually did anything
wrong, right? So and we are turning the situation into one where
there's only one possible conclusion when he shows up. Divorce without a
כתובה.
So there's a lower like necessary lower level of necessary evidence to
put someone through a סוטה Sotah ritual than to give them a
divorce without a כתובה. For sure.
A
divorce without a כתובה? No, not necessarily. I mean, there are cases
where a divorce could be without a כתובה even not based on
adultery and based on a whole series of inappropriate...
right, so there has to be good evidence. I mean, that's a
separate question, which we'll get to like in כתובות, Kesuvos, did we
do כתובות? Kesuvos? No. Okay, I'm getting lost where we are now
in נשים. Nashim. Anyway,
but anyway, but we'll get to that about like what type of
suspicions of adultery etc. But the simple case of סוטה, sotah. right,
is that even with just going through seclusion is enough of a
basis, it's not because now maybe you committed adultery, I mean, that
is, but it's because now you're סוטה sotah, and forbidden to your
husband, that the only result is גט. Get.
But there might be other cases without black and white evidence that's
enough to say divorce without a כתובה. That's a that's a discussion,
yes.
This is an adjudication process that's in between hearsay and solid evidence
of an act.
Right. Right. Well, but that makes that's fine if there's a way
if, I mean, if there's a way of resolving, you know, the
סוטות. Sotos. The interesting thing that we've seen in this משנה Mishna,
is that you can create that status even when from the outset
there's no possible end result of סוטות. Sotos. That was a whole
series of cases in the משנה Mishna, where we knew from the
get-go there would not be סוטות, Sotos, but you could create that
status where logically you would say, why does the תורה Torah allow
that status if it can't be resolved? But the point might be
no, if there's those suspicions and those things happen and the husband
wants, that should be enough to sort of say like, you know,
a suspected adulteress now makes her forbidden, you know, creates the status
even even without the possible resolution. One minute, so but anyway, but
the point again to repeat here is so might there be other
cases that he would come back? First of all, he could come
back and warn her again,
right? Or could he come back and find witnesses to create enough
circumstantial... maybe, okay, but bottom line is they're acting in a way,
you know, when you say they're stepping in on his behalf, I
was just saying like maybe we say
אסור לקנא, asur lekana, it's your own husband and he's passionate and
subjective, but בית דין Beis Din is an objective problem that they
want to address. But the question I want us to ask ourselves
is what have they achieved through this? They have not, I don't
think they have stopped her behavior, because once there's only one solution
and it's the worst one possible, what's certainly will not stop her
from continuing this? And to the degree to which they've protected his,
so why do they need to get in to protect his interests?
What, his financial interests? That's why they're getting involved presumably? Yeah, but
why is that their issue? The only other issue that I would
understand is that they're saying like, we think the guy needs to
divorce his wife given what we've seen. So we're gonna act in
a way to pretty much ensure that he's going to divorce his
wife. Okay, that, but I want the
question stands, why should a בית דין Beis Din get involved in
that?
No, because it's divorce because
not because we think he should divorce his wife because they're fighting
all the time. We think he should divorce his wife for halakhic
reasons, because she's committed adultery we suspect that she's committed adultery and
we don't want them right we don't want them to remain married
in that case, yes.
So can I infer from this that this is the same as
if he's, pinpoint he'll be able to take care of it if
he's, you know, let's say in a coma, right, which is the
equivalent I guess of שוטה shoteh in this kind of a case?
They would say forget this whole קינוי Kinoi thing, we'll just somehow
write them a גט?
Get? No, but we're not getting into that question about whether you
can do a גט Get for a guy who's in a coma.
That's not clear.
Yeah, but okay, fine, then they would just not do the סוטה
sotah. then, this קינוי Kinoi then, because there's no
way he's going to be able to ever resolve this? No, maybe
maybe they just want to punish her, and that's I guess the
other thing that we haven't looked at, you know, maybe it's not
going to stop her behavior, but maybe it's going to be a
warning for future women and it's gonna and we want to punish
her. So even if the guy is never able to give her
a גט Get because he's a שוטה, shoteh, he's never going to
get better, he's going to die or whatever, we... We have now
punished her that she's not going to get her כתובה. Right. So
I guess that's another way of thinking about it. It's not to
protect his interests and not necessarily to end this marriage, but it's
to prevent future types of cases. Right? If women see that when
their husband's in prison, they know that they can't go ahead and
do whatever they want, that there's going to be a response and
that they're going to be stripped of their כתובה, you know, as
a result, then hopefully that'll keep people in line. That can be
the נפקא מינה.
Nafka Mina. Right.
It is interesting. Okay. All right, guys, I'm with Chava, enough. I
don't know how we got onto all this. Okay. I know it's
interesting, but we have a דף to do. Okay.
משנה, Mishna okay, גמרא. Gemara משנה הוא דלא שתיא. Mishna hu d'lo
shatya. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, he doesn't, they, so in this case of ארוסה Arusa ושומרת
יבם, she can't be made to drink. הקינוי מקנא לה, Ha'kinoi mikanei
la, but presumably it's clear that you can do the קינוי kinnui.
and make her into a סוטה. sotah מנא הני מילי, Mna hani
mili, how do you get this middle stage? דתנו רבנן, D'tanu Rabbanan,
דבר אל בני ישראל ואמרת, Daber el Bnei Yisrael v'amarta, speak to
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael and you should say to them, איש איש
כי תשטה אשתו, Ish ish ki tisteh ishto, etc. So what's the
דבר ואמרת? Daber v'amarta? Which is funny because the גמרא Gemara often
makes a דרשה Derasha about that, but really it just says speak
saying the following, but it seems some, the גמרא Gemara seems to
feel that ואמרת v'amarta is superfluous. Always more. Oh, I don't know
if that's what it is. Anyway, maybe. לרבות ארוסה ושומרת יבם לקינוי.
L'rabos Arusa v'Shomeres
Yavam l'kinoi.
So to tell you that double language is that even an ארוסה
Arusa and שומרת יבם Shomeres Yavam, are in the פרשה, Parsha, even
a bigger category than you would have suspected. ומתניתין מני, U'masnisin mani,
רבי יונתן, Rabbi Yonasan,
he, and it's רבי יונתן. Rabbi Yonasan. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, Baraisa, where we're actually going to see that it's a
debate. תחת אישך. Tachat ishech. It says את כי שטית תחת אישך,
At ki satisa tachat ishech, that you strayed from your husband and
אישות Isshus here is the full marriage. פרט לארוסה, Prat l'Arusa, which
excludes the case of an ארוסה, Arusa which is not אישות. Isshus.
יכול, Yachol, I mean it's, again, paper marriage, but it's not a
full marriage. יכול שאני מוציא אף שומרת יבם, Yachol she'ani motzi af
Shomeres Yavam, now interestingly, against our משנה, Mishnah. the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma says here, maybe שומרת יבם Shomeres Yavam would not be able
to go through the process of סוטה. Sotah תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
איש איש, Ish ish, לרבות רבי יאשיה. L'rabos Rabbi Yoshiya. רבי יאשיה
Rabbi Yoshiya says the double language of איש איש Ish ish means
that a שומרת יבם, Shomeres Yavam actually there's enough of a marriage
there continuing from the dead brother that actually can make her go
through the whole סוטה Sotah. process even to the point of drinking.
רבי יונתן אומר, Rabbi Yonasan omer, תחת אישך, Tachat ishech, פרט לשומרת
יבם. Prat l'Shomeres Yavam. No, no, no. He says שומרת יבם Shomeres
Yavam. cannot make her go through the process, and not only that,
to me it's more obvious that the שומרת יבם Shomeres Yavam is
excluded than the ארוסה. arusah תחת אישך, Tachat ishech, the first person
I would exclude that's not the husband is the שומרת יבם. Shomeres
Yavam Now, where were we? פרט לשומרת יבם. Prat l'Shomeres Yavam. הוציא
שומרת יבם ולא הוציא את ארוסה, Hotzi Shomeres Yavam v'lo hotzi es
Arusa, maybe I won't exclude the ארוסה arusah case. תלמוד לומר, Talmud
lomar, אשר תשטה אשה תחת אישה. Asher tisteh isha tachat isha.
No, there's another תחת אישה, tachat isha, which means full marriage, פרט
לארוסה. Prat l'Arusa. So what you have to understand is there are
two debates, one Halakhic debate but one conceptual debate. The Halakhic debate
is that the first opinion,
רבי יאשיה, Rabbi Yoshiya, actually says that a שומרת יבם Shomeres Yavam
could be made to drink. Okay. Is treated like a normal wife.
And רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonasan is our משנה Mishnah, that says that
both an ארוסה arusa and a שומרת יבם Shomeres Yavam cannot be
made to drink. Okay, so the debate is: can a שומרת יבם
Shomeres Yavam. be made to drink? The other debate is which is
the more of the two, which is more obvious to exclude, to
say is not considered אשה, Isha, אישות? Isshus? Okay, so רבי יאשיה
Rabbi Yoshiya obviously thinks that an ארוסה arusa is more obviously to
exclude because he thinks that a שומרת יבם Shomeres Yavam. does drink.
But the other position, רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonasan says, no, the first
one I would exclude is a שומרת יבם. Shomeres Yavam, So what's
that debate about? So the גמרא Gemara says the following: מר אלימא
ליה ארוסה, Mar alima leh Arusa,
one of them thinks that an ארוסה arusa is more of an
אישות, Isshus, a woman that a man married, דקידושי דידיה, d'kiddushi dideh,
first of all, he initiated it, so he like, you know, there's
a conscious choice to make her, you know, his wife. וסוקלין על
ידה, V'soklin al yadah, and she's fully marriage, she would get סקילה
Skila if she committed adultery. So it's full marriage, like they're 100%
married, it's just they haven't begun to live together, but you know,
it was a choice of the two of them and it's completely
binding. Okay, and anyway, what?
Yeah, it's, it's kind
of,
they get, no, no, no. I mean, it might, it might not
be the same, but the question is, it's, it's the same as
נשואין. Nisuin. The question is, is it as, like which is weightier,
right? It's very, very weighty
if adultery is punishable by death. The nature
of the relationship is a very heavy one, it's a very weighty
one. Okay, so it's not that it's the same as נשואין. Nisuin.
It's just that it's more closer to full אישות Isshus than שומרת
יבם. Shomeres Yavam שומרת יבם, Shomeret Yabam, you didn't will it, it
was dumped on you, and the woman would not get a heavy
punishment if she committed adultery. So this is a much more weighty
relationship. So that's the one that you're more likely to include. ומר
אלימא ליה שומרת יבם, U'mar alima leh Shomeres Yavam, and the other
one says, no, שומרת יבם Shomeret Yabam? is more the one that
should be
included, דלא מחסרא מסירה לחופה, d'lo mechasra mesira l'chuppah, because it almost
happens automatically. You don't have to do a act of going to
the חופה, Chuppah, you don't need to precede it with— קידושין, you
just sleep together even if you're not intending to sleep together and
then it actualizes the sort of link into marriage that's already there.
So therefore there's more of a marriage that's present and ready to
be actualized. Okay, so so they have different approaches. Now, bottom line
though, רבי אושעיא, Rebbe Yoshiya, it's not just a hypothetical, רבי אושעיא
Rebbe Yoshiya in practice actually says that the case of שומרת יבם,
Shomeret Yabam. the brother, and again it's a real good question if
there's multiple brothers, but we'll bracket that, the brother can make her
drink, you know, even, you know, for suspecting her and can make
her go through the whole process, whereas the ארוס arus cannot. Okay,
so that's really and that's רבי אושעיא, Rebbe Yoshiya, that's not our
משנה. Mishnah, So now let's see the גמרא Gemara continues with that
debate. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Oh, I'm sorry,
the other point though is, so based on the פסוק pasuk of
תחת אישך, tachat ishech, we exclude one or both of these women
from going through the process. On the other hand, from the פסוק
pasuk of דבר אל בני ישראל ואמרת, daber el Bnei Yisrael ve'amarta,
we include them in the פרשה parshah to some degree. So how
do we balance that? They're included in the פרשה parshah for the
beginning of the פרשה. parshah. What's the beginning of the פרשה? parshah?
דבר אל בני ישראל ואמרת daber el Bnei Yisrael ve'amarta is right
at the beginning. That's the קינוי. kinnui. They're excluded where it says
תחת אישה tachat ishah or תחת אישך, tachat ishech, which is the
end of the פרשה, parshah, which is the drinking. So they're excluded
from the drinking but they're included in the קינוי.
kinnui You may know you're going to feel jealous but you can't
do anything.
No, what you can do, you warn, no, no, again, remember, קינוי
kinnui, for the גמרא Gemara is a legal process. Right, you warn
her and she goes into seclusion and that makes her forbidden as
a סוטה. sotah. Whereas if we would say she's excluded from קינוי,
kinnui even if the husband was jealous and warned her and seclusion,
she wouldn't have the halachic status.
Once you go through these stages, halachically she's a סוטה, which means
they're forbidden to sleep together.
But we have no process for resolving it. Right, which is the...
Well, he can give her a divorce. Exactly, and then no סוטה.
Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, האי איש איש מאי עביד ליה?
hai ish ish mai avid leh?
What does רבי יונתן Rebbe Yehonatan do with איש איש ish ish
which רבי אושעיא Rebbe Yoshiya used to include the case of שומרת
יבם? Shomeret Yabam, So מיבעי ליה לרבות אשת חרש ואשת שוטה ואשת
שימום, mibai leh lerabot eshet cheresh ve'eshet shotah ve'eshet shimum,
to include the case that the בית דין Beit Din can at
least the בית דין Beit Din can represent and do קינוי kinui?
for the wife of a חרש, cheresh, the wife of a שוטה,
shotah, and what's שימום? shimum? שימום shimum seems, more רש"י Rashi says,
לקוי בתמהון לב, lakui bitmihon lev,
it seems like another case of a mental like a fugue state
or something. Not so much of a mental illness in terms of
processing reality, but more just unable fundamentally to like be able to
relate to reality. רבי אושעיא Rebbe Yoshiya למה לי דאי שימום? lama
li dei shimum? That's the
let's focus. רבי אושעיא, Rebbe Yoshiya, so רבי אושעיא Rebbe Yoshiya says,
האי תחת אישה מאי עביד ליה? hai tachat ishah mai avid leh?
So רבי אושעיא, Rebbe Yoshiya, what does he do with תחת אישה?
tachat ishah? Because תחת אישה tachat ishah for רבי יונתן Rebbe Yehonatan
excluded a שומרת יבם. Shomeret Yabam, So רבי אושעיא Rebbe Yoshiya who
includes a שומרת יבם, Shomeret Yabam, what does he what does he
do with תחת אישה tachat ishah which seems to exclude certain cases?
So מיבעי ליה להקיש איש לאשה ואשה לאיש. mibai leh lehakeesh ish
le'ishah ve'ishah le'ish. Okay,
to connect the man to woman, woman to a man. What that's
about we'll get to in like two days. Let's not worry about
that right now. Fine. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא
טעמא דכתיב הני קראי. ela ta'ama dechtiv hani krai. So the reason
that, you know, we are excluding an ארוסה arusa. or שומרת יבם,
Shomeres yavam and or שומרת יבם, Shomeres yavam, not or, whatever. Anyway,
is because of the verse, the פסוק pasuk says it's not full
אישה, ishah, and that's why they're being excluded. הא לאו הכי, ha
lav hachi, if it wasn't for the verse of אישה, ishah, הוה
אמינא ארוסה שתיה, hava amina arusah shatya,
that an ארוסה arusa. could be made to drink, right, if it
was not for that word that suggests it had to be a
full marriage. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, וכי אתא רבי
אחא בר חנינא מדרומא אתא ואייתי מתניתא בידיה. vaki ata Rabbi Acha
bar Chanina mi'droma ata ve'aisi masnisa bideih.
He came and he brought the following ברייתא baraita in his hand.
And this is what I referred to earlier, which isn't in the
משנה, but is a teaching that the גמרא Gemara that's presented here
that the גמרא Gemara embraces, and it's the following teaching. It says,
מבלעדי אישך ויתן איש בך את שכבתו מבלעדי אישך, miba'aladei ishech ve'nitein
ish bach eshchavto miba'aladei ishech,
and a man lied with you other than your husband. So that's
the פסוק pasuk and the דרשה drashah is the following: משקדמה שכיבת
בעל לבועל. mishekadma shchivas ba'al le'boel.
You could only do the process of סוטה if the husband and
wife have consummated their marriage before she might have had sex with
another man. Okay, so he had to have been there first, essentially.
ולא שקדמה שכיבת בועל לבעל. velo shekadma shchivas boel le'ba'al. But if
they never consummated their marriage and then she was suspected of sleeping
with another man, he would not be able to make her undergo
this process. Now that's very interesting, right, what is that about? I
mean, one way about thinking about that is it's the type of
point of similar to our משנה, which is, what do you call
it, which is the degree of אישות, ishus, right? Only if the
marriage has like fully been actualized and realized and not even that
they've just started living together and stood under a חופה, chupah, but
they've actually been intimate and have sex, only at that full stage
of אישות, ishus, right, only then is when he is able to,
you know, to be in that sort of position to, to do
this. It could be, one also though wonders, and I don't know
if I've raised... this before,
but
there definitely seems to be,
people say this from a position of evolutionary biology, but the רמב"ן
Ramban also says it just from פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim,
there seems to be a concern, one of the main concerns or
a possible serious concern about adultery, is the concern about raising another
man's children, right, about like if another man slept with my wife
then those children are not mine. And that's the concern about the
issue about
זרע. zera. Okay, so
the פסוק pasuk is ושיכב איש אותה שכבת זרע ונעלם מעיני אישה.
Veshachav ish otah shichvat zera vene'elam me'einei ishah. Why
does it say שכבת זרע? shichvat zera? הלכתית Halachically it would be
the same issue if they had sex without
ejaculation. So we don't even interpret
שכבת זרע shichvat zera הלכתית. halachically. We ignore that point. It has
to be maybe ראוי לביאה, ra'uy levi'ah, whatever. Anyway, but what's the
point? So the רמב"ן Ramban says the point is that the reason
the man is so jealous is because there's this concern about like
deep deep down which he might not even articulate to himself, it's
like, if another man slept with my wife then are these my
kids?
Okay, and so that is actually interesting just to say an aside,
Rav Moshe Feinstein basically had no problem with the idea of artificial
insemination using another man's sperm, because obviously any concept of adultery or
whatever only comes through an act of sex, so even if it's
another man's sperm, big deal. And other פוסקים poskim like the ציץ
אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer said, what are you talking about? It's quasi-adultery and
the children would be quasi-ממזרים,
because another man's sperm even without sex is pretty much adultery is
what he said. And he quotes the רמב"ן Ramban on the פרשה
parsha of שכבת זרע shichvat zera where the רמב"ן Ramban says that's
what the concern of adultery is, that it's another man's seed. So
another man's seed even without sex, it's almost like it's adultery. So
Rav Moshe in a fascinating תשובה tshuva basically said like, I don't
know what he's talking about, I only, he's obviously being influenced by
outside values, these are not תורה true values, I only do הלכה,
I'm not influenced by such stuff, which is so fascinating because it's
actually like פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, it's a פשט, pshat,
the רמב"ן Ramban says it, and like this dismissing of this as
completely foreign values. But anyway, from a legal position, it's not adultery
without an act of sex. The reason I raise all of this
here is because is it possible a man is concerned that they're
not his kids if he's never had sex with his wife? Sure,
but nevertheless, I think first of all then he'll know they're not
his kids if he's never had sex with his wife. But I
think that again what we see this focus
on like זרע, zera, my kids,
my etcetera, ונקתה ונזרעה veniktah venizre'ah is the end of the פרשה
parsha as well. So I do think that that might be a
piece of this idea about why like they have to have already
consummated their marriage for this whole פרשה parsha to be relevant.
Yeah, but why is the connection made between זרע zera and other
man's children and adultery as opposed to קינוי? kinui. In other words,
I could understand every time you see that child the feeling
of rage and jealousy come up again.
Right, right, but it's
not exactly the same as adultery because you could have an adulterous
act without producing.
Right, I'm not sure what you're saying.
I'm just saying. I'm not saying adultery is only about that, but
I'm saying that that's a part of what fuels
the קינוי. kinui The קינוי kinui is a piece of what's going
on.
It's a גלגול, gilgul, you could still get her for those other
timeframes.
That's true, okay, let's go on. Okay, so anyway, but that's a
very important and interesting הלכה that it can only apply once it's
been consummated. So אמר רמי בר חמא משכחת לה כגון שבא על
ארוסתו בבית אביה. Amar Rami Bar Chama mashkachat lah kegon sheba al
arusato beveit aviha. That's to drinking it or that?
That's a good question.
Let's say to drink it, certainly to drink it, that's actually a
very good question, I don't know, I have to check on that.
But why did we have to exclude an ארוסה arusa while it's
got to be to drink it because you could make an, you
could do קינוי by an ארוסה Arusa, without having had sex, right,
so it would only be to drink. So why do we have
to exclude an ארוסה from a פסוק pasuk of תחת אישה, tachat
ishah, let's just exclude her from drinking because they haven't had sex
yet with her husband, okay. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רמי
בר חמא משכחת לה כגון שבא על ארוסתו בבית אביה. Amar Rami
Bar Chama mashkachat lah kegon sheba al arusato beveit aviha. Ah no,
maybe she did have sex with her husband while she was still
an ארוסה. There they were, she's still living in her father's house,
the emphasis of בבית אביה beveit aviha is they haven't made home
together, she's still living in her father's house, it's the period of
betrothal, but they got a little carried away so they had sex
before the חופה, chuppah, okay, and she would still be an ארוסה.
Now by the way, in כתובות Ketubot we will find out that
that actually was the מנהג minhag in יהודה which is that they
would go in
private, they wouldn't דווקא davka have sex, but they'd spend time together
in private after the אירוסין eirusin and the גמרא Gemara acknowledges that
sometimes it would lead to sex. But nevertheless, sex does not automatically
make a woman who's an ארוסה into a נשואה when it's not
in the context of beginning the married life, when it's not in
the context of נישואין. nisuin. רש"י Rashi is actually interesting, רש"י says
ארוסה בבית אביה בזנות. arusa beveit aviha biznut. So I assume what
רש"י means when he says
בזנות. biznut. But I assume he means not in the context of
now we're beginning our married life together. Okay, so anyway, so it
is possible, so that's how you have. So the גמרא Gemara says,
and that's why in that scenario we would have thought that he
could make her drink and the פסוק Pasuk says he can't make
her drink. So now the גמרא continues,
כהוותה גבי שומרת יבם? Kehavta gabei shomeres yavam? One minute, but how
do you have the case of שומרת יבם Shomeres yavam? where they've
had sex where she's not yet his wife? As soon as they've
had sex, right, anybody remembers, you know, יבמות, Yevamos, even if it's
like unintentional for—well, you know, whatever the—you know, whatever the circumstances are,
automatically that actualizes the full אישות. Ishuta. So how can you have
a case, why do we need to exclude according to רבי יונתן
Rabbi Yonatan on שומרת יבם, Shomeres yavam if you'll never have a
scenario where they've already had sex and her still being a שומרת
יבם? Shomeres yavam So the
גמרא says—that's what the גמרא says—כהוותה גבי שומרת יבם כגון שבא עליה
יבם בבית חמיה, Kehavta gabei shomeres yavam kegon sheba aleha yavam beveit
chamiyah, like the יבם had sex with her while he was in
her father-in-law's house, meaning some researchers say that way, while she was
in her let's say dead husband's house, maybe after her husband died
she went to live with his with his father anyway. השומרת יבם
קרי לה? Hashomeres yavam karis lah? You're calling her still a שומרת
יבם Shomeres yavam if they've already had sex? אשתו מעלייתא היא! Ishto
me'aleta hi! דאמר רב, De'amar Rav, רב Rav says, קנה לכל דבר,
Kanah lechol davar, that even if they have sex with the case
of שומרת יבם Shomeres yavam not in the context of starting of
like of starting the the
marriage, you know, they just have sex like בזנות Biznut as it
were, רב Rav still says that that—I don't care what the context
is, you know, it's a full
marriage.
Okay, so her dead husband's father, חמיה, Chamiyah, right, okay.
So, so, so what's the case where you have שומרת יבם Shomeres
yavam after sex that you needed the פסוק Pasuk to exclude it?
So the גמרא says, כשמואל דאמר לא קנה אלא לדברים האמורים בפרשה.
KeShmuel de'amar lo kanah ela ladevarim ha'amurim baparsha. No, שמואל Shmuel says
that if they're having sex but it's not in the context of
starting the marriage, if they're having it בזנות Biznut as it were,
then yes, she's legally his wife and if she were to commit
adultery she'd be, you know, she'd—she'd—it would be a capital crime, etc.
And להקים שם אחיו המת, Lehakim shem achiv hamet, if, you know,
she—he now inherits his dead brother's estate. Those things are true, but
it is not full נישואין, Nisuin, okay, until you basically plan for
it to be a married life together, you know, you have something
similar to a חופה, Chupah, like you have sex in the context
of נישואין, Nisuin, it's not full נישואין. Nisuin. So it's sort of
like a—I mean he doesn't say that, she's legally 100 percent his
wife now, again adultery would be a capital crime, other things that
apply to the פרשה, Parsha, להקים שם אחיו, Lehakim shem achiv, etc.,
but it's more like אירוסין Erusin and not like נישואין. Nisuin.
But he still has to support her, right?
Yeah. So anyway, but the גמרא says, so according to שמואל, Shmuel,
you could have it a type of a שומרת יבם Shomeres yavam
after sex, and that's what you needed the פסוק Pasuk to exclude,
okay, because she's not fully his wife and the same way it
excludes an ארוסה, it could exclude this שומרת יבם Shomeres yavam after
they'd had sex. So the גמרא says, אי הכי לימא רב דאמר
כרבי יאשיה ושמואל דאמר כרבי יונתן? Ihachi leima Rav de'amar keRabbi Yoshiya
veShmuel de'amar keRabbi Yonatan? Oh,
so let's say therefore
that רב, Rav, who says that it is—after sex they—she's fully his
wife, so for him he must say like רבי יאשיה, Rabbi Yoshiya,
because רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya says that the שומרת יבם Shomeres yavam
does drink. So now we understand why רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya says
the שומרת יבם Shomeres yavam, does drink. It's a little funny, the
שומרת יבם Shomeres yavam does drink because there's no such thing as
a שומרת יבם, Shomeres yavam because basically after they've had sex she's
his
wife. And שמואל, Shmuel, who says the שומרת יבם Shomeres yavam, doesn't
drink—I mean, שמואל Shmuel says that she's not fully his wife, says
like רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan that she doesn't drink. That sort of
matches up. So the גמרא says—we'll just do the answer—אמר לך רב,
Amar lach Rav, רב Rav would tell you, no, אנא דאמרי אפילו
רבי יונתן, Ana de'amri afilu Rabbi Yonatan, I could say like רבי
יונתן Rabbi Yonatan that the שומרת יבם Shomeres yavam. after sex doesn't
drink. מדיצטריך קרא למעוטי, Mideitztrich kra lemoutei, since you needed a פסוק
Pasuk to exclude a שומרת יבם, Shomeres yavam, מכלל דאשתו מעלייתא היא,
Miklal de'ishto me'aleta hi, so without the פסוק Pasuk I would have
said 100 percent his wife. But—but now the פסוק Pasuk is telling
you—now this is crazy—now according to רב, Rav, what we're saying is
that they had sex, she's 100 percent his wife, right, after יבום,
yibum, right, the act of יבום, 100 percent his wife, nevertheless, the
whole פרשת סוטה Parshas Sotah doesn't apply. Because why? Because it's not
a marriage that he chose, because it's a continuation of the brother's
marriage. Meaning until now, the reason you can't do the סוטה is
because the marriage was not yet complete. רב Rav is now saying,
I could in theory say that the פסוק Pasuk is teaching you
that after sex, because it's coming through יבום, that nevertheless that's excluded
from the category of סוטה. Okay, let's just finish one more line.
ושמואל אמר אנא דאמרי אפילו רבי יאשיה, VeShmuel amar ana de'amri afilu
Rabbi Yoshiya, I would say even like רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya who
would—who would include a שומרת יבם. Shomeres yavam מדיצטריך קרא לריבויי, Mideitztrich
kra lerabuyei, if you needed the פסוק Pasuk to include שומרת יבם,
מכלל דלאו אשתו היא כלל, Miklal delav ishto hi klal, it means
that she's not fully his wife. So yes, I mean, that's what
we were thinking until now, yes, a שומרת יבם is not fully
his
wife. So שמואל Shmuel could say, I would say after sex if
done בזנות, b'znut, she's not 100% his wife, and nevertheless, even though
not 100%, she's enough in the פרשה parsha to be included for
the drinking of the סוטה. And רב Rav could say, I would
say that after sex she's fully his wife, and nevertheless, since it's
coming through יבום, she's excluded. Okay? And with that we conclude
today's דף. All the best.